Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Library of Congress
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Library of Congress
N/A
manu Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
Harned, Thomas Biggs
poetry Manuscripts
Manuscripts Division, The Library of Congress The Library of Congress, Manuscripts Division Room LM101, James Madison Building 101 Independence Ave., S.E. Washington, D.C. 20540-4680 http://www.loc.gov
This catalog was created, in part, from digital images of the original manuscripts obtained by The Walt Whitman Archive. The original papers and the finding aid completed by Michael McElderry are held at the Library of Congress.
Restrictions:
None
Scope and Content
The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman spans the period 1842-1937, with most of the items dated from 1855-1892. The collection consists of Whitman's correspondence, poetry and prose manuscripts, notes and notebooks, proofs and offprints, printed matter, and miscellaneous supplementary items. A detailed description of the Harned Collection can be found in the Library of Congress publication Walt Whitman: A Catalog ( 1955 ), which contains an introductory essay on significant Whitman collectors and their collections and an annotated bibliographic listing of Whitman items then located among the collections of various divisions within the Library.
Walt Whitman's papers were divided among his three literary executors, Richard M. Bucke, Thomas Biggs Harned, and Horace L. Traubel. Of these, only Harned's collection remains largely intact, the integrity of the other collections having been lost through dispersal. Whitman's personal habits were such that he wrote and collected his notes in a casual and unsystematic manner, entrusting his thoughts to scraps of paper, be it the back of a used envelope or the verso of a letter. His notebooks contain an equal number of random jottings, some no more than bits and pieces of paper sewn together to form a small notebook. These notes and notebooks include names and addresses, trial titles, trial lines of poetry and prose pieces, diary and hospital notes, pencil sketches and drawings, drafts of poems and essays, autobiographical and personal notes, printing and publishing notes, and miscellaneous notes on a wide range of subjects such as history, geography, politics, and ethnology.
Poems and prose writings in the Manuscripts series vary in form from tentative outlines to final drafts. This material often shows the extensive revision characteristic of Whitman's composition. Related notes and notebook entries add details helpful for textual analysis of the poems. Whitman's practice of drafting letters, notes, and literary works on the back of incoming letters necessitates the identification of verso items in order to provide full documentation.
James R. Osgood printed the Boston edition of Leaves of Grass ( 1881-1882 ), which was withdrawn from publication after being censored by local authorities. Correspondence between Osgood and Whitman about this edition is contained in the collection, as are letters exchanged with T. W. Rolleston concerning German and Russian translations. Other correspondents include Anne Burrows Gilchrist, Thomas Biggs Harned, William Sloane Kennedy, James M. Scovel, J. M. Stoddart, and Benjamin Holt Ticknor.
Whitman had been greatly moved by Abraham Lincoln, who symbolized for him the best in the American national character and who inspired some of his greatest poetry. He lectured extensively on Lincoln, and in a series of lectures given between 1879 and 1890, he recalled details of Lincoln's life and death and sketched an intimate profile based on personal reminiscence. The Lincoln Material series contains a thematic grouping of various types of manuscripts and printed matter concerning these lectures and related topics.
The Proofs and Offprints series includes copies of Whitman's prose and poetry. Whitman often revised his writings after having them set in type, and several of the proofs in this series contain either corrections to the text or notations for the printer.
In 1942, a group of Whitman notebooks from the Harned collection, along with other national treasures, were evacuated from Washington, D.C., for safekeeping during World War II. Upon the return of the material from storage in 1944, it was discovered that ten Whitman notebooks and a cardboard butterfly were missing. In 1995, the Library regained custody of four of these notebooks and the butterfly, but six notebooks remain unaccounted for.
The recovered items relate to Whitman's early career as a journalist and poet and include notes on perception and the senses, names and addresses, diary notes, drafts of Civil War poems, and observations made in Washington, D.C., during the Civil War. Whitman also used the notebooks to record the public's reaction to and acceptance of his poetry. The earliest notebook in the collection, written between 1847 and 1854, was among the four recovered and contains drafts of one of Whitman's most famous poems, Song of Myself. Other notebooks contain notes Whitman made while working as a nurse in Civil War hospitals in Washington, 1862-1864. The cardboard butterfly is thought to be the same Whitman wired on his finger in a photograph that was published as the frontispiece for the 1889 birthday edition of Leaves of Grass.
Only those items deemed poetry and/or prose manuscripts are described in this catalog.
Biographical Information
Thomas Harned was a prominent lawyer in Camden, New Jersey, where Whitman lived in his final decades. He was a close friend of Whitman's and one of three literary executors named in Whitman's will.
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Manuscripts; Poets, American--19th century
Item List
- Notes and Memoranda, 1856-1888 and undated (Box 1, Box 2)
  Holograph fragments, notes and fragments, partial manuscripts of essays, autobiographical pieces, lectures, and other prose writings. Arranged chronologically.
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated; loc.00622; xxx.00655; poetry 4 leaves handwritten (Box 2, Folder Undated, Miscellaneous notes or reminders)
    Notes Whitman took concerning ideas or suggestions for poems and other work (for example, "Mr. Goodfellow's suggestions for a pastoral poem"). These notes have no known relationship to Whitman's published work.
  - Summer Rivulets, 1875-1881; loc.05635; xxx.00142; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder Trial titles)
    In this manuscript Whitman mentions a plan to write a "piece strongly recognizing the affiliations" of his poems. In a centered column, there are three possible titles for such a piece, and one of them is "By the road-sides," which is resonant with the title Whitman would give to the cluster By the Roadside first in the 1881-1882 edition and then in the 1891-1892 edition of Leaves of Grass.
  - [Centennial Ed'n], 1875-1876; loc.05636; xxx.00905; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder Trail titles)
    A draft advertisement, with information about price, binding and contents, for the Centennial Edition of Leaves of Grass, published in 1876. The manuscript is almost identical (with the exception of "Italian boards" instead of "Italian card") to a manuscript held at the University of Virginia (see uva.00163).
  - [He Went Out With the Tide], 1885-1891; loc.01159; xxx.00387; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder [1865 or before], war and hospital notes and memoranda)
    This manuscript contains a passage used in a note (entitled "Another Note") to the poem An Ended Day published in 1891 in Good-Bye My Fancy 2d Annex to Leaves of Grass.
  - [Drifts & Bubbles], 1875-1876; loc.05073; xxx.00922; xxx.00489; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder Trial titles)
    This manuscript contains a list of trial titles and subtitles which were possibly considered by Whitman when he was preparing the Centennial edition of Leaves of Grass together with its companion volume, Two Rivulets, published in 1876.
  - [Century Thoughts], 1875-1876; loc.05074; xxx.00922; xxx.00489; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder Trial titles)
    This manuscript contains a list of trial titles which Whitman possibly considered to use in Two Rivulets, the companion volume to the Centennial edition of Leaves of Grass published in 1876.
  - [Walt Whitman's Centennial], 1875-1876; loc.05075; xxx.00922; xxx.00489; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder Trial titles)
    This manuscript contains a few trial titles which Whitman possibly considered to use when he was preparing the Centennial edition of Leaves of Grass together with its companion volume, Two Rivulets, published in 1876.
  - How Would it Do, 1880-1885; loc.05173; xxx.00469; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Undated, on the American Idiom)
    This manuscript contains a draft with trial titles and general ideas for the essay Slang in America, published in the North American Review ( November 1885 ). The piece was later reprinted in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and was retained in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Allude to the Suez, 1869-1871; loc.05312; xxx.00496; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1-2, Folder Miscellaneous notes or reminders)
    This manuscript contains a short reminder about alluding to the Suez Canal. The Suez Canal would appear for the first time in Whitman's poetry in Passage to India, published in the 1871 edition of Leaves of Grass, and the reference was retained thereafter.
- Notebooks, 1847-1885 and undated (Box 2-3)
  Notebooks containing diary entries, drafts, literary notes, names and addresses, sketches and drawings, and trial titles. Arranged chronologically. Selected copies of portions of six missing notebooks, made prior to their disappearance, are located in the Photocopies and the Supplementary Papers series.
  - Note Book Walt Whitman, about 1855; loc.00346; xxx.00048; handwritten prose poetry 14 leaves (Box 2, Folder Notebooks, Before 1855)
    A notebook which contains a draft of The Poet (see surfaces 20 and 21). Some of these lines appear to contribute to the poem ultimately titled Song of Myself, first published in 1855.
  - Talbot Wilson, 1874–1854; loc.00141; xxx.00001; handwritten prose poetry 66 leaves (Box 8, Folder Recovered Cardboard Butterfly and Notebooks, Notebooks, [1847], (80))
    Early discussions of this notebook dated it in the 1840s, and the date associated with it in the Library of Congress finding aids is 1847. The cover of the notebook features a note calling it the "Earliest and Most Important Notebook of Walt Whitman." Recent scholars, however, have argued that Whitman repurposed this notebook, and that most of the writing was more likely from 1853–1854, just before the publication of Leaves of Grass. For an explanation of the reasons for the confusion, and a discussion of the fascinating history of this notebook into the twentieth century, see Matt Miller, Collage of Myself: Walt Whitman and the Making of Leaves of Grass (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2010 ), 2–8. See also Andrew C. Higgins, Wage Slavery and the Composition of Leaves of Grass: The Talbot Wilson Notebook, Walt Whitman Quarterly Review 20:2 (Fall 2002), 53–77. Scholars have noted a relationship between this notebook and much of the prose and poetry that appeared in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. See, for instance, Edward Grier, Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts (New York: New York University Press, 1984), 1:53–82. The notebook features an early (if not the earliest) example of Whitman using his characteristic long poetic lines, as well as the "generic or cosmic or transcendental 'I'" that appears in Leaves of Grass (Grier, 1:55). For the full transcription of this notebook, see http://www.whitmanarchive.org/manuscripts/notebooks/transcriptions/loc.00141.html
  - Notebook, 1860-1861, loc.00029; xxx.00131; prose poetry handwritten 61 leaves (Box 2, Folder Notebooks, 1860-1861)
    An early notebook with several notes for poem ideas, trial lines, addresses, and drawings. Material in this notebook relates to poems ultimately titled Out of the Cradle Endlessly Rocking, By Blue Ontario's Shore, The City Dead-House, and Chanting the Square Deific. Some of the trial verses in this notebook were published posthumously as [I Stand and Look], Ship of Libertad, and Of My Poems. Within the notebook is also a poem draft that Whitman has titled called The Incomplete.
  - [Other-Leaves], 1845–1892; loc.04602; xxx.00999; poetry handwritten 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder Undated, Notebook pages)
    Notes for a potential work concerning lines and processions, with the words "Other-Leaves/ Dust-and-Spray" at the top.
  - Dr. L B Russell, 1862-1863; loc.05449; xxx.00965; xxx.00485; prose 43 leaves handwritten (Box 2-3, Folder Diary)
    This manuscript notebook contains a series of diary entries from December 1862 to December 1863. In the entries, Whitman keeps track of family correspondence and of how he spent his days. He often mentions visiting wounded and dying soldiers in Washington military hospitals. While the whole notebook adds context to Whitman's writings about the Civil War, there are two entries that can be directly linked to specific passages in Whitman's published work. The entry from Monday, May 4th, 1863 (surface number twelve) mentions "4th Hooker's battles around Fredericksburg to night the wounded begin to arrive from Hooker's command." This passage contributes to the section The Wounded from Chancellorsville published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-1883 ) and retained in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The entry from Wednesday, September 16th, 1863 (surface number thirty-one), reporting the death of Lorenzo Strong, contributes to Last of the War Cases published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later retained in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [Collected in], 1863-1867; loc.06101; xxx.00524; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder Notebooks)
    The seventh surface of this manuscript notebook contains a passage that will appear, with revisions, in the article Democracy published in the Galaxy ( December 1867 ). The passage will also appear in Democratic Vistas ( 1871 ) and retained in Democratic Vistas and Other Papers ( 1888 ) and in Democratic Vistas published within Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Address Book, 1867-1875; loc.02821; xxx.00983; xxx.00262; prose poetry 52 leaves handwritten print (Box 3, Folder [1866-1877], address books)
    A disbound notebook, mostly filled with names and addresses. However, the sixty-first surface contains an idea for a poem about "The Storm / all the various things that happen in a storm." It is possible that this is an early conception of the poem that would eventually be titled Proud Music of the Storm (originally titled Proud Musc of the Sea-Storm). The note mentions being "at sea," as well as "sleeping" and "wak[ing]," all of which are ideas found in Proud Music. The range of dates in the notebook also falls within the likely period of compositon for that poem, with an earliest recorded date of January 1867 (leaf 18). Proud Music of the Sea-Storm was first published in the February 1869 issue of the Atlantic Monthly, but was completed by 30 November 1868, when Whitman sent a copy of the poem to Ralph Waldo Emerson.
  - Hospital notebook, 1863-1864; loc.05356; xxx.00980; prose 49 leaves handwritten (Box 3, Folder Washington & Brooklyn hospital notebook)
    A handmade notebook (now disbound) containing mostly names and addresses of soldiers and brief accounts of the hospital camps and battlefields. Two of the soldiers' names, Rueben Farwell and Bethuel Smith, appear in Typical Soldiers, a section of Specimen Days ( 1882-1883 ). The piece was reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Note Book, 1860; loc.04605; xxx.00981; prose poetry 34 leaves handwritten (Box 2, Folder [1860], Boston notebook)
    A notebook from Whitman's trip to Boston in March through May of 1860. While most of the notebook is devoted to names, addresses, and notes from his visit, the first two leaves (surfaces 3 and 4) contain notes related to the printing of the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass, which he was in Boston to oversee. The printing notes refer to possible ornamentations for specific pages of Leaves and reference other books as examples of possible ornamentation and typography. Edward Grier provides information about the specific books that Whitman mentions, noting similarities between them and Leaves (Notebook and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts [New York: New York University Press, 1984] 1:419-421). Images of blank versos for several of the pages are currently unavailable.
  - July 30 1865, 30 July 1865; loc.02818; xxx.00485; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 3, Folder Notebook pages [1865])
    Two manuscript leaves containing notes from Whitman's Civil War hospital visits. These particular notes would later be included in Army Hospitals and Cases: Memoranda at the Time, 1863-66, published in Century Magazine in October 1888. The piece would later be revised and included in November Boughs as Last of the War Cases.
  - a schoolmaster, 1842-1852; loc.04588; xxx.00511; poetry prose 11 leaves handwritten print (Box 2, Folder Notebooks c. 1852?)
    An early notebook, mostly containing the outline(s) of one or more pieces of early fiction. The name of one character, "Mr. Covert," appears in Whitman's story Revenge and Requital; A Tale of a Murderer Escaped, first published in the United States Magazine and Democratic Review in July–August 1845. The piece would be revised and/or reprinted several times in various publications before ultimately appearing as One Wicked Impulse! in Specimen Days ( 1882–83 ). While the name "Mr. Covert" connects the notebook with One Wicked Impulse! there are only minor similarities between the plot-points of the two. It is thus possible that this notebook contains notes towards a different, as-yet-undiscovered piece of early fiction. Whitman has also pasted two Tribune clippings (surface 5) and copied two excerpts of poetry (surface 19). The first poetic quotation comes from Robert Blair's poem The Grave ( 1743 ). The source of the second quotation is unknown. The cover of the notebook is labeled "Note Book Walt Whitman 82" in a hand that is not Whitman's. A complete transcription of a schoolmaster is available on The Walt Whitman Archive.
  - America to the Old World Bards, 1870-1891; loc.04599; xxx.00395; poetry 3 leaves handwritten (Box 3, Folder Notebook pages)
    A manuscript containing poetic lines that eventually led to the poem Old Chants, first published in the New York publication Truth on 19 March 1891 and was later reprinted in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ). "Nat Bloom," the name that appears on the recto of the third leaf, was a New York City acquaintance of Whitman from as late as the 1870s, according to Edward Grier (Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts [New York: New York University Press, 1984] 4: 1405). If that is true, then this constitutes a very early draft of Old Chants.
  - Life light and, 1860-1867; loc.04601; xxx.00048; poetry 2 leaves handwritten (Box 3, Folder Notebook pages)
    A manuscript that contains various poetic lines. The line on the second leaf that describes "the Steamship... and the trailing pennant of smoke" was incorporated, in a slightly altered form, into the 1867 version of the poem that would eventually be titled Song of Myself. The line was retained in all subsequent versions of the poem. The connection of the rest of the lines to Whitman's published work is unknown. The versos of both leaves are currently unavailable.
- Correspondence, 1866-1891 and undated (Box 3-4)
  Letters to and from Whitman, drafts of outgoing letters, and postcards. Arranged sequentially by catalog item number.
- Newspaper Clippings on the Civil War, 1866-1891 and undated (Box 4)
  Newspaper clippings on the Civil War and various miscellaneous Whitman manuscript fragments and notes.
  - [O a new song], about 1861; loc.00103; xxx.00177; handwritten printed poetry 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder Newspaper Clippings on the Civil War)
    A manuscript fragment containing the first two partial lines of the poem Song of the Banner at Daybreak first published in 1861 as Banner at day-Break. The fragment has been pasted to a larger sheet making the verso unavailable.
  - Abraham Lincoln, 1878-1879; loc.05588; xxx.00531; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 4, Folder Lincoln material, 1865-1868)
    This manuscript contains what could be a preparatory note for the lecture Death of Abraham Lincoln delivered in New York in 1879, in Philadelphia in 1880 and in Boston in 1881. Portions of this lecture had been originally published as Abraham Lincoln's Death. Walt Whitman's Account of the Scene at Ford's Theatre, in the New York Sun ( 12 February 1876 ) and were included in Memoranda During the War ( 1875-1876 ). Abraham Lincoln's Death was revised and published as A Poet on the Platform in the New York Daily Tribune ( 15 April 1879 ) and was subsequently reprinted as Death of Abraham Lincoln in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-1883 ) before finally appearing in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Manuscripts, 1859-1892 and undated (Box 1)
  Holograph drafts, notes and trial lines of essays, poems, and prose writings. Organized by type of material and arranged chronologically therein.
  - Leave-taking Words, 1870–1876; loc.00078; xxx.00131; xxx.00496; xxx.00030; poetry 1 leaf 23.5 x 13.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Out of the Cradle Endlessly Rocking)
    The page appears to be a draft of a title page for a manuscript titled Leave-taking Words or Last Ripples (A Prelude to Passage to India). At the bottom of the page are four lines from the end of Out of the Cradle Endlessly Rocking, first published as A Child's Reminiscence in 1859. The lines from the poem are cleanly written, suggesting that they were meant to serve as an epigraph for Whitman's manuscript. Passage to India was published first in 1871. On the verso is a draft of a stanza of Eidólons, first published in 1876. The verso also contains prose comments on the war, of which the connection to Whitman's published works is unknown.
  - Out of A Hundred Years, after 1865; loc.00079; xxx.00131; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Out of the Cradle Endlessly Rocking)
    A scrap of paper with an underlined title written across the top reading Out of A Hundred Years and subtitled "in Prose and Verse Melanged." In the top margin is written "?Vistas."
  - [Surgeons operating], about 1865; loc.00080; xxx.00188; poetry prose 1 leaf 21 cm x 16.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder A March in the Ranks Hard Prest)
    A clean, late draft of lines published in the poem A March in the Ranks Hard-Prest, and the Road Unknown, first published in 1865. On the verso are prose notes about various corps of Civil War soldiers.
  - [Again with latest breath], about 1874; loc.00081; xxx.00263; poetry 1 leaf 16 cm x 13.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Prayer of Columbus)
    Early draft of lines contributing to Prayer of Columbus, first published in 1874. On the verso is a draft of Whitman's prose introduction to the poem.
  - [some threading Ohio's], 1881; loc.00082; xxx.00224; poetry correspondence 1 leaf 13 cm x 14.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder As Consequent, etc.)
    A draft of lines of As Consequent, Etc., first published in the 1881 edition of Leaves of Grass. On the verso in a letter from the Camden and Atlantic Railroad dated January 25, 1881.
  - A starry midnight, about 1881; loc.00083; xxx.00291; poetry 1 leaf 21 cm x 13 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder A Clear Midnight)